# Suhail F. Qadir

Email: suhail.qadir@gmail.com

Mobile (Qatar): (+974) 7702-7556 Tel (USA): (+1) 661-442-5397

## **CAREER SUMMARY**

I posses over 33 years of rich and diverse professional experience in the consultancy, engineering and project management for building, infrastructure and architectural industry, including eight years in the Middle East, with internationally renowned and recognized consultants and PM/CM companies.

A self-motivated, quick learner with strong consultative skills. Recognized for analyzing complex situations and innovative thinking to improve design and production processes while optimizing integration of technology. A proactive thinker who sets clear goals and delivers tangible results within targeted timeframe.

Seeking challenging roles in Project / Design Management. Demonstrated skills include:

| ■ Design Management                  | <ul><li>Contract Administration</li></ul>      | <ul> <li>Institutional Building Design</li> </ul> |
|--------------------------------------|--|---|
| <ul><li>Project Management</li></ul> | <ul><li>Specification Administration</li></ul> | <ul><li>Organization</li></ul>                    |
| ■ Facilities Management              | Hospitality Industry Design                    | <ul><li>Urban Planning</li></ul>                  |

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## ASTAD Project Management, Doha, State of Qatar

2010 - To Date

A joint venture between QF and QP; ASTAD is a leading indigenous project management consultancy to have delivered number of prestigious projects in Qatar and is now expanding its horizon to the entire MENA region.

## Project Manager - ASTAD Project Management, Doha, Qatar.

Qatar Economic Zone 3 (QEZ3) is a 34.2 km² area located adjacent to Mesaieed Industrial City & Hamad Port. Project plans to host downstream & specialty metal, petrochemical, building materials, other manufacturing, logistics park, maritime industries and supporting activities, in addition to labor accommodation and supporting commercial activities. It host 90,000 population with 1629 plots amounting to 1160 Ha GFA

## Portfolio Project Coordinator (51 projects) - ASTAD Project Management, Doha, Qatar.

Entrusted with overall progress, coordination and high-level problem resolution, involving management direction, of around 51 projects, in excess of QR 2.84 billion, in the Education City precinct, Qatar Museum Authority and Aerospace City predominantly on infrastructure, building design coordination and construction.

#### Qatar Petroleum, Doha, State of Qatar

2009 - 2010

QP is Qatar's largest conglomerate and has evolved in-house capability for design, project and construction management expertise in oil & gas and infrastructure projects. It manages all its onshore and offshore projects and shares its expertise with numerous government, semi-government and private organizations.

### Senior Project Engineer - Qatar Petroleum Complex Project, Doha, Qatar.

Worked on a landmark Corporate Office Campus based on innovative and unique design by Skidmore, Owings & Merrill with approximately 420,000m<sup>2</sup> gross area on a lot size of 550,000m<sup>2</sup> having project value of QR 8 **(\$2.2)** billion. The precinct caters to 4,800 employees, and 4,200 structured parking.

Responsibilities included design & project management covering pre-design to tender award, QP's specialized process. Coordination with authorities and statutory agencies forms part of day-to-day business and collaboration with specialist consultants is the core business.

## Bovis Lend Lease Int. Ltd., Central Europe, Middle East & North Africa region (CEMEA) 2007 - 2009

Bovis Lend Lease is the world's premier project management and construction company with a presence in over 30 countries for on and offshore projects. Key areas include construction, project management, design & design engineering and procurement through a workforce of over 12,000 employees worldwide.

## Senior Design Manager - International City Phases 2 & 3, Dubai UAE

Primarily an infrastructure project with a cost of AED 2.5 billion (\$685 million), the role entailed complete architectural / structural design of the development of 731 hectare Nakheel initiative including design and implementation of standard services in addition to gas, CCTV network and district cooling with emphasis on sustainability by way of landscape and extensive use of recycled TSE and other sources. The development comprises of 1,280 parcels with varying land use for a net total floor area of 9.7 million m² and housing a population of 152,000 inhabitants.

Lead a dedicated team of six professionals with roles and responsibilities as follows:

### • Design Management

Landscape: Consultancy value of AED 6.1 (\$1.67) million for a landscape area of 97.3 hectares.

Successfully concluded design, program, deliverable, review, coordination and contract management of landscape design for the entire development. This required an intense and involved collaboration with a foreign offshore consultnat for a complex and challenging role.

**CCTV:** Client afterthought arising from a royal decree and posing complexity of retofitting both in design and implementation. Managed extensive infrastructure coordination with various stakeholders for fairly advanced stage of construction.

# Suhail F. Qadir

Email: suhail.qadir@gmail.com

Mobile (Qatar): (+974) 7702-7556 Tel (USA): (+1) 661-442-5397

**Wayfinding & Signage:** Initiated consultant engagement by preparing Client Brief and SoS. **Facilities Management / Service Charge Model:** 

- Prepared Client Brief and Scope of Services specific to the Development.
- Coordinated to achieve integration with existing design and deliverables.

**Waste Management:** Corroborated with Client team to develope and finalize a progressive and sustainable waste management strategy for the Development. Implement this strategy through incorporation into Development Code and TPD design review process.

- **TPD (Third Party Developers) Design Management:** Nakheel delegated statutory role of building design reviews and approvals of individual lots in the light of Development Code:
  - Authored, edited and revised Development Code
  - Incorporated sustainability initiatives with administrative / utilities updates to the Development Code.
  - Maintained public office forefront to address TPD related matters.
  - Ongoing revamping of processes / procedures to facilitate smoother / faster design review handling.
  - Reviewed and verifed legal land documents for the Development before issue by the Client.

#### • Master Plan Related Activities:

- Prepared and revised Master Plan for changes required by service providers, statutory authorities, infrastructure design updates and changes in the light of Client direction.
- Prepared reports, statiscal analysis, proposals, studies and reviews on numerous on demand requirements as required by the Client from time to time.

## DSA Architects International, Dubai, UAE

2005 - 2007

An architectural practice ranked among the first 20 in the world based on company size and number of architects. It has offices in South Africa, Middle East and Europe. Completed Madina Jumeirah, company's first landmark project in Dubai.

## Senior Project Architect - Dubai UAE

Responsibilites included management of all aspects of design construction documentation and external works achieved through a team of six professionals in addition to involved coordination with all other related building services disciplines. Noteworthy projects are:

- Fairmont Resort Hotel, Palm Jumeirah, Dubai: (Project cost of AED 550 million (\$151 million). Salient design features included layout of 415 key guest rooms, offshore design of restaurant and residences posing unique logistic and MEP coordination challanges, special MEP transfer floor, custom designed acoustic treatment for noise control of VIP suites, gas farm design for LPG / NG torches, blast proof structure design etc.
- Rani-Oberoi Hotel, Business Bay, Dubai: Designed fire protection and fire fighting strategies.

#### CigNET, North Carolina, USA

2004 - 2005

Consulting Company providing a variety of project management and construction related services. The scope of services covered a wide variety of commercial, residential and institutional projects. Also catered to project cost analysis and contract management.

Project Manager - Birkdale Village, Charlotte, North Carolina, USA

The project is built on 52 acres of land with 200,000 feet<sup>2</sup> at a project cost of \$132 million.

 Participated in the Project Management of infrastructure design, master planning and building designs of numerous small to medium sized mixed used developments in Charlotte-Meclenburg area.

## TIAA-CREF, Denver (Colorado) & Charlotte (North Carolina), USA

1998 - 2004

A Company ranked 68<sup>th</sup> in the Fortune100 companies with over \$315 billion in assets.

**Technical Consulting Manager (Architecture) –** Charlotte, North Carolina, USA (2001 – 2004) Construction of new Corporate HQ campus on 160 acres of land with gross built up of 2.13m ft<sup>2</sup> Responsibilities included:

- Design management
- Construction co-management
- Post construciton Facilities Mangement with high degree of flexibility for special business needs.

## **Technical Consulting Architect (FM)** – Denver, Colorado, USA (1998 – 2001)

Participated in a major expansion initiative for strategic regional hub, backoffice and DR (Disaster Recovery) center. The Coordinated relocation of several hundered employees for setting up new office facilty as required by each business unit. Also worked with special office space requirements for housing a large server farm room and mainframe. Coordinated with electrical, mechanical and HVAC for special cabling, heating, cooling and acoustic standards.

#### CENTURA HEALTH, Denver, Colorado, USA

1997 - 1998

One of the largest Health Care systems in Colorado, maintains 12 hospitals with 12,400 employees

# Suhail F. Qadir

Email: suhail.qadir@gmail.com Mobile (Qatar): (+974) 7702-7556 Tel (USA): (+1) 661-442-5397

Coordinator Hospital Expansion Project – Denver, Colorado, USA (1997 – 1998)

Assisted in the Centura Health's largest 300 bed hospital major upgrade project. The team concluded the project handling all aspects of infrastructure / MEP design and implementation with careful consideration to the integration with existing systems and custom / specialized hospital needs.

#### MINISTRY OF DEFENSE, RAWALPINDI

1990 - 1995

The Centralized Design Bureau catering to the design needs of Army, Air Force and Navy. This office handled both urban design and architecture and handled projects worth several million dollars annually.

Principal Architect: Managed a team of 30 personnel including six design engineers.

Responsibilities included design of structure, architecture, master planning and landscape disciplines for projects ranging from large military regional Head Quarters, military cantonments with extensive residential planning to accommodate division level soldiers to div commander, hospitals, offshore design and implementation of residences. The urban planning work encompassed design of new large military bases and extension of existing cantonments. Noteworthy achievements follow:

- Design, architecture / structure and MEP coordination, and implementation of offshore military accommodation off of Karachi Naval Base.
- Design of 300 bed Gilgit CMH (Combined Military Hospital) on fast track.

### HOUSING & PHYSICAL PLANNING DEPARTMENT, GOVERNMENT OF PUNJAB

1982 - 1990

The agency develops and maintains large industrial estates and satellite housing colonies throughout Punjab. The agency also caters to the commercial / retail and parks / recreation facilities in their land development.

## Assistant Director Design, Lahore

Responsibilities included management of a team of five to cater to the urban design and city planning for large satellite towns and neo urban settlements. Other areas of responsibity included design of housing colonies, parks and recreation facilities (complete with infrastructure design), commercial / retail buildings and industrial zone building permits and standards enforcement.

- Designed satellite urban developments in Sahiwal, Rawalpindi, Vehari, Multan and Okara.
- Participated in review and change of urban design policies and guidelines as an ongoing process.
- Printed a number of publications related to standardized low cost housing for low income groups.
- Installed and monitored computer based data collection and code enforcement of Industrial Estates owned by the Department.

### **BKM Associates, Lahore**

(1979 - 1982)

A consulting company of international fame and winner of several national competitions. The company has pioneered a contemporary style based on indigenous architectural elements and materials.

#### Architectural Design Intern, Lahore

- Participated, as a team member, in major design competitions of national stature.
- Prepared unique intricate details based on company pioneered design style.
- Produced detailed contruction drawings for several commercial projects.
- Assisted in project planning and monitoring of a UN sponsored large low cost housing project.
- Designed and published several commercial advertisements and graphic art.

#### Personal Details

| Date of birth: 22 December 1959                     | • Language Command: English, Urdu, Punjabi                      |
|---|---|
| Nationality: American (USA).                        | Hobbies: World economy, philately, gardening, professional      |
| • Sports followed / played: Swimming, table tennis, | technical reading, computer hardware & software specific to new |
| American football and basketball.                   | emerging technologies related to profession.                    |

### **EDUCATION**

- Masters of Architecture / Urban Planning (secured 3.7 GPA), University of Colorado at Denver 1997 Emphasis on transportation, road designs, environmental impacts and infrastructure design achieved through Advanced Computer Aided Design, 3D Modeling and GIS Systems.
- Bachelor of Architecture, University of Engineering & Technology, Lahore, 1982
   Thesis on Islamic Research Center with integrated library, Madrissa, conference center and mosque.

|--|

| <ul> <li>The Coaching Clinic, TIAA-CREF, USA</li> </ul>              | ■ Producing Results with Others, TIAA-CREF   |
|--|--|
| <ul> <li>USGBC LEED Certification Preparatory Course, BLL</li> </ul> | ■ IIF (Incident & Injury Free) Passport, BLL |